Sincro: wyxchari
【翻译】巴蛮子sz
【时间轴】巴蛮子sz
【校对】巴蛮子sz
基于 opentitles.org 英文字幕翻译
他的脸，他的头发，你看!
His face, his hair - look at it!
他还在呼吸...
He's breathing...
...而且TARDIS看起来很正常
...and the TARDIS seems to be normal.
Ben, 我们该怎么办? 我们不能把博士扔那儿不管.
Ben, what are we going to do? We can't just leave the Doctor there.
什么, 他是博士?
What, him? The Doctor?
嗯，从门外走进来的人就是他 - 外面也没有其他人
Well, that's who came through the doors - there was no one else outside.
Ben, 你记得他在跟踪室内说过什么吗? 好像说＂我的旧身体穿了身新皮囊. "
Ben, do you remember what he said in the tracking room?
Something about "This old body of mine is wearing a bit thin. "
这么说他有了个新的?
So he gets himself a new one?
嗯，是的.
Well, yes.
哦，得了吧!
Oh, do me a favour!
Ben, 这里肯定发生了点什么.
Ben, whatever happened, happened in here.
但这不可能啊!
But it's impossible!
不久以前，我们还对好多事情说了这句话.
Not so long ago we'd have been saying that about a lot of things.
哦, Ben!
Oh, Ben!
慢点... 慢点!
Slower... Slower!
聚焦在一个东西上... 就一个!
Concentrate on one thing... one thing!
过去了
It's over.
博士?
Doctor?
肌肉还有点紧.
The muscles are still a bit tight.
我们该做点什么?
What are we going to do?
他是博士. 我就知道... 我觉得.
It is the Doctor. I know it is... I think.
不仅仅是他的脸变了 - 他的行为也不像.
It's not only his face that's changed - he doesn't even act like him.
来吧，我们把这事搞清楚.
Come on, it's time we sorted this out.
现在看这儿!
Now look here!
停住.
Hold that.
斜点儿
And tilt it.
你干过这个吗?
Have you done with this?
放下，放下.
Put it down, put it down.
现在，玩什么游戏?
Now, what's the game?
啊!
Ah!
十字军，撒拉丁
The crusades, from Saladin.
博士是个收藏家啊!
The Doctor was a great collector, wasn't he!
但你就是博士啊!
But you're the Doctor!
哦，我看着不像他.
Oh, I don't look like him.
我们是谁?
Who are we?
你不知道吗?
Don't you know?
Extermination! (Daleks 常用口号，意为"毁灭／终结"）
（博士手里是一块来自Daleks的金属板）
Extermination!
啊!
Ah!
啊，很好，指甲得长长.
Ah, very good. Nails need growing.
看，博士总戴着这个，如果你是他，这个应该大小合适，对不对?
Now look, the Doctor always wore this.
So if you're him, it should fit now, shouldn't it?
看 - 掉下来了.
There - that settles it.
我想看看蝴蝶展开翅膀后怎么适应它的蛹
I'd like to see a butterfly fit into a chrysalis case
after it's spread its wings.
你真的变了!
Then you did change!
生命依赖于变化... 和新生.
Life depends on change... and renewal.
哦，那就是了 - 你已经重生了，是吧?
Oh, so that's it - you've been renewed, have ya?
我已经重生了，是吗？应该是了，我重生了!
I've been renewed, have I? That's it, I've been renewed!
这是 TARDIS 的能力，没有它，我就不可能幸存.
It's part of the TARDIS - without it, I couldn't survive.
过来!
Come here!
到这里来.
Come here.
博士持有一本日记，对吧?
The Doctor kept a diary, didn't he?
是的.
Yes.
我记得是，不过现在在哪儿呢?
I thought so. Now, I wonder where?
在哪儿呢?
I wonder where?
他真跟博士有点不同, Ben.
He's a very different Doctor, Ben.
嗯, 很可能. 不过我们现在到底什么情况?
Yeah, maybe. Just where do we stand, though?
博士? 博士, 我们会怎样?
Doctor? Doctor, what's going to happen to us?
我觉得... 我觉得我们着陆有一阵子了. 我觉得我们该出去逛逛了.
I think... I think we must have landed for sometime.
I think it's time we went for a stroll.
但你都不知道我们着陆到哪里了!
But you don't know where we've landed!
别，你还没有检查氧气和温度，什么都没还没检查！
No, you haven't checked the oxygen or the temperature or anything!
氧气浓度172，辐射零，温度86
Oxygen density one-seven-two, radiation nil, temperature... eighty-six
有较强的水银沉淀. 满意了吗, Ben?
strong suggestion of mercury deposits. Satisfied, Ben?
现在，你们两个来还是不来?
Now, are you two coming or are you not?
他真认识我们! 他喊你 "Ben", 听到了吧?
He does know us! He said "Ben", didn't you hear him?
是的，听到了. 但他可能只是听到你说了，是吧?
Yeah, I heard. But he might just have been copying you though, mightn't he?
噢 不要!
Oh no!
来不来，你俩?
Are you coming, you two?
我得试一试你，我觉得!
Time I put you through some tests, I think!
哈罗?
Hello?
哈罗? 有人吗? 哈罗?
Hello? Is there anyone there? Hello?
哈罗? 他们怎么还不来?
Hello? Why don't they come?
啊, 你终于来了. 我从地球来的. 我是监察员...
Ah, so you've come at last. I'm from Earth. I'm the Examin...
"地球监察员. 授予所有权限. Vulcan. "
"Earth Examiner. Accord every access. Vulcan. "
博士?! 你在哪儿?
Doctor?! Where are you?
喔, 好热!
Whoa, they're hot!
唔, 是不是到处的空气都像这样?
Hmm, do you think the air's like this everywhere?
不 - 可能只是这一片才这样. 别使劲吸气, 我知道的.
Nah - might be just round here.
Don't want too many lung full of it, I know that.
我小的时候住在一家酒坊对面. 还没走完一趟人就醉了!
Here, when I was a kid, we used to live opposite a brewery.
You could take a walk and get tipsy all in one go!
好美啊!
It's beautiful!
别，别碰, Polly!
No, don't touch it, Polly!
我没打算碰.
I wasn't going to.
这是水银 - 会从这些气泡里面出来.
No, it's quicksilver - it gets through the pores.
博士要去哪儿啊？ - 就算他是博士吧
Where is the Doctor, or whatever he is, got to?
什么情况? 嘿, Polly!
What's the matter? Hey, Polly!
嘿，博士 - 你在哪儿! 快点, Polly这里出事了!
Hey, Doctor - wherever you are!
Quick, there's something happened to Polly!
快点，这边!
Quick, over this way!
博士!
Doctor!
啊, Quinn, 你在这里啊. 你在这里发现了什么?
Ah, Quinn, there you are. What have you got there?
我的人在其中一个池子边还发现了两个.
My people have found two more of them by one of the pools.
这个人脑后受了严重的伤. 然后晕倒了, 我估计。
This one's got a nasty bruise on the back of his head.
Fallen over his feet and knocked himself out, I suppose.
我也觉得.
I suppose so.
他们怎么不用我们送给他们的器材呢？
Why don't they use the kit we send them?
是的，另两个人也吸入了烟气 - 至少那个女孩儿是.
Yes, the other two have had a rather bad dose of fumes - the girl has anyway.
女孩?
Girl?
是, 但她会恢复的.
Yes, but she'll recover.
你这些着装搞笑的保安总算还有点作用.
These comic-opera guards of yours do have some uses after all.
他们是按身体素质挑选出来的.
I pick them for their physical fitness.
我也觉得不是按他们的智商. 帮一下监察员，行吗.
I thought it wasn't for their I.Q.
Give me a hand with the Examiner, will you.
我很好奇地球为什么要送一个监察员到 Vulcan 来? 我是说，为什么现在?
I wonder why Earth has chosen to send an Examiner to Vulcan? Just now, I mean?
我不知道.
I don't know.
一个谜题啊. 他应该两年后才上任的.
A mystery, isn't it? He isn't due for another two years.
你感觉如何?
How do you feel?
哦...
Oh...
我们看到你们的火箭飞出着陆区了.
We saw your rocket overshoot the landing area.
哦?
Eh?
别担心 - 大多数地球来的飞船都会飞出去. 我是 Quinn, 这里的副总督.
Don't worry - most of the ships from Earth do over-shoot.
I'm Quinn, Deputy Governor.
Bragen, 安保队长.
Bragen, Head of Security.
我们回去吧? 我负责带这个女孩儿.
Let's get all back shall we? I'll take the girl.
来，你们俩，帮忙扶一下监察员.
Here, you two, help carry the Examiner.
我想你们几位地球来的，等不及要看看 Lesterson 的太空舱了吧?
I suppose you Earth people can't wait to examine Lesterson's space capsule?
嗯?
Eh?
Lesterson?
看这里.
Look at this.
他们刚带进来了一位地球来的监察员，还有几位助手．
They've just brought in an Examiner from Earth, and a couple of assistants.
监察员? 来干什么?
An Examiner? What's he here for?
我以为你知道.
I thought you'd know.
啊，冲着太空舱来的，一定是.
Ah, it's the capsule, it must be.
他们不可能拦着我继续搞这个，我跟你说.
Well, they can't stop me working on it, I can tell you that.
有人能嘛?
Could anyone?
总督那里就一直不好搞. 但他们当然不会从地球送个人过来，只为了...?
The Governor's always been difficult about it.
But surely they wouldn't send someone all the way from Earth just to...?
那，会面怎么办?
Look, what about the meeting?
会面?
Meeting?
是的 - 我都已经安排好了. 我们可以继续使用旧的火箭室吗?
Yes - I've arranged everything. Can we still use the old rocket room?
是的，我觉得可以. 但我觉得你不要把这些压力集团搞混了, Janley.
Yes, I suppose so. But I do wish you wouldn't get mixed up
with these pressure groups, Janley.
这样，总有人得做点什么. 这块基地在走下坡路了，你知道的.
Well, somebody has to do something.
The colony's running down and you know it.
啊，我太忙了.
Well, I am too busy.
但如果我们有所动作的话，你就能有更好的设备，更多的钱．我期望你上点心.
But if we ran things, you'd have better facilities, more money.
I wish you'd take an interest.
看, 我并不介意你常常来借用我的房间, Janley, 但别把我扯进去.
Now look, I don't mind letting you have the use of
one of my rooms now and again, Janley, but don't try to involve me.
这才是我觉得重要地位东西. 在水银沼泽里待了两百年...
This is what I find important.
Two hundred years in a mercury swamp...
...这片金属是从上面掉下来的. 看 - 花几分钟抛光一下就跟新的一样了.
...and this piece of metal that dropped from it.
Look - a couple of minutes polishing and it's as good as new.
漂亮.
Wonderful.
雨水, 湿气, 热浪, 水银 - 什么也不能侵袭这块金属. 没有锈斑, Janley - 想想吧.
Rain, damp, heat, mercury - nothing touches this metal.
No corrosion, Janley - think of that.
只是, 我期望监察员能允许你继续你的实验.
Well, I hope the Examiner lets you go on with your experiments.
坦白的说, 我有点怀疑.
Frankly, I doubt it.
我觉得总督让监察员过来就是为了阻止你打开太空舱的.
I think the Governor's brought the Examiner here
to stop you opening the capsule.
你该加入我们组的, Lesterson. 某天你会需要我们.
You should join our group, Lesterson. You might need us one day.
所以被谋杀的人就是真的监察员?
So the murdered man was the real Examiner?
那么，你有没有看到是谁干的?
Well, didn't you see who did it?
博士, 这里多了颗纽扣.
The Doctor got this button though.
我觉得这挺无聊的. 我不明白我们为什么不回到 TARDIS 去.
Well, I think it's pretty dull around here.
I don't know why we don't just go back to the TARDIS.
博士，你是想让他们觉得你就是真正的监察员吗?
Doctor, are you going to let them think you're the real Examiner?
嗯，那会不会比较危险?
Well, won't that be dangerous?
看，你能不能不再吹那个，认真跟我们说说?
Look, why don't you stop blowing that thing and talk to us properly?
Ben!
你现在别说话 - 跟他在一起就够糟的了!
Now don't you start - it's bad enough with him!
他什么也没做.
Well, he hasn't done anything.
不，那就是麻烦所在! 他知道那会儿 TARDIS 里发生了什么
No, that's just the trouble!
He knows what happened back at the TARDIS,
他会告诉我们吗? 他会站出来说? 他会承认他就是博士?
yet will he tell us? Will he come out and say?
Will he admit to being the Doctor?
请进!
Come in!
我是 Hensell - 这里的总督. 我想想你们感觉好点了吧?
I am Hensell - the Governor.
I trust you're all feeling much better?
唔，我感觉更差了，总督.
Huh, I've felt worse, Governor.
总督?
The Governor?
如果地球早点告诉我们你要来，我们就可能可以帮助你着陆了.
If Earth had seen fit to warn us you were coming, we might,
possibly, have been able to guide you down to the landing area.
如果地球没告诉你，总督，他们一定有一个很好理由. 我很好奇到底是什么?
If Earth didn't warn you we were coming, Governor,
they must have had a very good reason. I wonder what it was?
你看 - 我负责这块基地. 我有权知道你为什么到 Vulcan 来. 简单说说?
Now look here - I run this Colony. I'm entitled to know
why you've come to Vulcan. What is your brief?
我是监察员.
I am the Examiner.
为什么来这儿?
Why are you here?
监察. 我现在就要开始检查!
To examine. And I intend to start my examination at once!
有人密报说这里有人叛乱，是为了这个吧，是吗?
Someone's leaked reports about these rebel groups
- that's it, isn't it?
该你了，总督.
Your turn now, Governor.
应该是 Lesterson 的那个舱体.
There is Lesterson's capsule.
内部事物归我管， Bragen. 请不要来干扰我们!
Internal affairs are my business, Bragen.
Please don't interfere!
请继续.
Please go on.
这个舱体，是在一个水银沼泽里发现的. 可能在那里已经几个世纪了.
The capsule. It was found in a mercury swamp.
It must have been here for centuries.
有意思 - 继续.
Interesting - continue.
在地球殖民者到达前的几个世纪. 我觉得它可能很危险, 它可能带有细菌.
For centuries before the Earth colony arrived.
I felt it might be dangerous, it might contain bacteria.
我应该检查一下这个舱体... 待会儿吧. 你们可以走了
I shall examine the capsule... later. You may leave us.
我期待你的报告.
I shall look forward to your report.
Bragen, 确保监察员和他的随从 ... 换身得体的衣服，好吧?
Bragen, see that the Examiner and his party...
get some proper clothes, will you?
我们穿得很得体!
We are wearing proper clothes!
哦，他怎么拿回那个东西的? 有点厚颜无耻吧?
Oh, how did he get that thing back again?
That was a bit of a cheek, wasn't it?
呃，看看总督能不能把他个徽章拿下来?
Er, seeing if the Governor was the guy that you got the button off?
博士?
Doctor?
唔?
Mmm?
他跟你说话的时候，你盯着其他人看?
When he was talking to you, you were staring at the other man?
是的，我太失礼了，是吧? 可怕的修养.
Yes, very rude of me, wasn't it? Terrible manners.
跟你说实话吧，我是在研究他的反应 - 看他是否赞同那个故事.
To tell you the truth, I was studying his reactions
- seeing if he agreed with the story.
他赞同吗?
Did he?
得看一眼那个舱体.
Must have a look at that capsule.
你最好注意一下, 扮演监察员不要过于投入了.
You know, you wanna watch you don't take this Examiner stuff a bit too far.
我们的答案只能从那个水银沼泽里面寻找.
Our answers must come from that mercury swamp.
因为至少有一个家伙不会被骗.
'Cos at least one bloke ain't gonna be fooled.
Bragen 找到我们的时候，他绝对说的是“太空”舱.
When Bragen found us, he definitely said space capsule.
你骗不了那个把真监察员召来的人!
Look, you're not going to fool the guy that did the real Examiner in!
Bragen! 为什么见一下监察员还得先征得同意?
Bragen! What's all this nonsense about
having to have a pass to see the Examiner?
这是总督的主意.
It's the Governor's idea.
当然这对我不适用吧?
Surely it doesn't apply to me?
不是我下的命令, Quinn. 我觉得总督不想让人靠近他.
It's not my order, Quinn.
I expect the Governor wants to keep people away from him.
听起来像是你们这类 red-tape 的主意.
It sounded like one of your red-tape ideas.
这跟我没关系.
It has nothing to do with me.
正确!
Right!
哦!
Oh!
对不起, Janley.
Sorry, Janley.
我的错.
My fault.
你没事吧?
Are you all right?
是的. Lesterson 刚把我从实验室赶出来了.
Yes. Lesterson's just cleared me out of his lab.
监察员会允许他打开舱体吗?
Is the Examiner going to let him open the capsule?
我不知道. 我正在往那边走... 如果我能挤过 Bragen 的保安人墙的话.
I don't know. I'm on my way there now...
if I can push past Bragen's army of layabouts.
你在哪里得到这个的?
Where did you get this?
从舱体上掉下来的.
It dropped from the capsule.
掉下来?
Dropped?
是的, 把它拖进实验室的时候.
Yes, when it was being hauled into the laboratory.
不过，你看! 这种金属可以会对我们的太空旅行技术产生革命性影响.
But, you can see! This metal could revolutionise space travel.
这也是为什么我坚持要打开舱体. 谁知道里面还有什么其它神奇的东西?
That's why I'm insisting that we open it.
Well, who knows what other marvels there may be inside?
不过 Lesterson, 我没想到你能打开它?
But Lesterson, I didn't think you could open it?
我有一个理论. 我推断打开的方法是在两端，要么这边，要么这边.
Well, I have a theory. I'm convinced that the opening
mechanism on the other side is either here, or here.
Extermination...
终结...
我的理论是可以在这个背脊处注入激光束.
Now, my theory is that I can insert a laser ray in this ridge here.
光束散开, 触发开门设备，我们就可以进去了.
The ray spreads, fuses the opening device and gets us in.
监察员, 我觉得该你来决策了.
Examiner, I shall have to make it your responsibility.
激光? 没问题? 不会太难.
A laser? Why not? It shouldn't be too difficult.
我们来试试另外一边.
Well, we'll try the other side.
唔, 有一点... 让人失望.
Hmm, it's a bit... disappointing.
不会. 这只是门廊, 对吧?
Not really. This is just an entry bay, isn't it?
是的... 我觉得是.
Yes, I... I suppose so.
那并没有让我们走多远是吧?
Well, this doesn't get us very far does it?
进到舱体其它部分就需要时间了，总督.
Ah, getting into the rest of the capsule will take time, Governor.
你不能再用一下那个光束吗？那肯定是一个门.
Well, can't you use that torch thing again?
That must be an opening door.
我得考察一下，看看锁机关在哪儿.
Well, I should have to measure it up
and find out where the lock mechanism is.
我觉得今晚就到此为止吧.
And I think we'll leave if for tonight.
到此为止?
Leave it?
就这样了? 那我们来这儿干什么?
Leave it for tonight? But what did we come here for?
这是我的决定，总督.
That is my decision, Governor.
但是，苍天在上!
But, good heavens above, man!
两百年，你说它被埋了?
Two hundred years, you say, this has been buried?
哦，至少有. 里面的隔间里一定有什么东西.
Oh, at least. Now, there must be something in the inner compartment.
我们应该可以搞明白它是从哪里来的.
We shall be able to find out where it came from originally.
它并不是来自这个星球 - Vulcan.
It didn't come from this planet - Vulcan.
哦，不不不. 这个金属很外星.
Oh no, no, no. The metal is quite alien.
外星，是的. 非常外星. 晚安.
Alien, yes. Very alien. Goodnight.
他这是怎么了?
What's he up to now?
Ben, 不要让他离开我们的视线.
Ben, we're not going to let him out of our sight.
好了，Lesterson, 你有路子. 不过你找来这监察员值得吗? 就这个愚蠢的家伙?
Well, Lesterson, you got your way.
Was it worth sending for this Examiner? This idiotic Examiner?
不是我找你的. 我还以为是你呢.
I didn't send for him. I thought you did.
你为什么不让我跟监察员说话，Hensell? 我能找出他来这里的原因.
Why don't you let me talk to the Examiner, Hensell?
I can find out what's he's here for.
不不不, 你离他远点. 我们让他跟 Lesterson 呆一起吧.
No, no, no, no, you keep away from him.
We'll leave him to work with Lesterson here.
我们都有太多事情要做，负担不起来自地球的业余批评.
We've all got enough to do without having to worry about
some amateur critic from Earth interfering.
但只要５分钟, 我 _...
But with five minutes, I _...
你听到我的话了, Quinn. 你不介意让监察员忙得团团转吧, Lesterson?
You heard what I said, Quinn.
You won't mind keeping the Examiner busy, Lesterson?
我不介意你跟他做什么 ... 只要他的鼻子别到我的事情里面来到处嗅.
I don't mind what you do with him so long as you keep his nose...
out of our business.
好. 没问题.
Yes. All right.
就这样. 我们明早再讨论.
All right. Well, we shall talk about it tomorrow.
Ben!
什么?
What?
嘘! 他在走廊里.
Shh! He's in the corridor.
谁?
Who is?
博士, 你个笨蛋! 过来 - 快!
The Doctor, you clod! Come on - quick!
他往 Lesterson 的实验室去了.
He's going towards Lesterson's lab.
当然 - 那个太空舱!
Of course - to the space capsule!
快点.
Come on.
Polly, Ben, 进来见见 Daleks.
Polly, Ben, come in and meet the Daleks.
什么?
What?
Daleks.
The Daleks.
你以前就打开过这个.
You could have opened this before.
这两片金属是一样的. 其中一片是博士直接从 Daleks 那里得到的.
These two pieces of metal are identical.
The Doctor got one of them from the Daleks himself.
为什么你一直说“博士怎样怎样”，但你意思是在说你自己?
Why do you keep saying the Doctor if you mean you?
我知道我可以在这里找到他们 - 我就知道.
I knew I should find them here - I knew it.
啊, 他们看起来是无害的, 并不活跃.
Ah, they look harmless, not very lively.
你想什么呢? 在沼泽里呆200年，你也看起来不活跃
What do you think? Two hundred years in a swamp
and you wouldn't look very lively either.
没有什么东西能熬过来，是吧?
Nothing could live through that, could it?
活的?
Live?
不是人类, 不.
Nothing human, no.
博士, 看!
Doctor, look!
怎么回事?
What's the matter?
这里本来有三个 Daleks 的! 另外一个发生了什么?
Well, there were three Daleks in here!
What's happened to the other one?